<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oates's manifesto; or, the complaint of Titus Oates against the doctor of Salamanca; and the same doctor against Titus Oates: comprized in a dialogue between the said parties, on occasion of some inconsistent evidence given about the horrid and damnable Popish Plot.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27531</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99888450</idno>
  <idno type="VID">201976</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240896443</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O66</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide T.88*.[61]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230099</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99888450</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99888450e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 201976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C30:1[60])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Oates's manifesto; or, the complaint of Titus Oates against the doctor of Salamanca; and the same doctor against Titus Oates: comprized in a dialogue between the said parties, on occasion of some inconsistent evidence given about the horrid and damnable Popish Plot.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. MDCLXXXIII. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Oates, Titus, 1649-1705 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:201976:1"/>
            <p>OATES'S Manifesto; OR, THE COMPLAINT OF TITUS OATES AGAINST THE Doctor of Salamanca; AND, The same DOCTOR AGAINST TITUS OATES: COMPRIZED in a DIALOGUE Between the said PARTIES, On occasion of some Inconsistent EVIDENCE Given about the Horrid and Damnable POPISH PLOT.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>De Ore tuo Te Judico.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. L.</hi> Anno Dom. MDCLXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:201976:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IF the Publisher had not been too hasty, the <hi>Preface,</hi> and the <hi>Book</hi> should have come out together; For the Reader is to be advertis'd, that the <hi>Contradictions</hi> and <hi>Inconsistencies</hi> which are here expos'd in this following <hi>Dialogue</hi> betwixt <hi>TITUS</hi> and <hi>OATES,</hi> are only a <hi>General Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> out of the <hi>MASS</hi> of his EVIDENCE, without any special regard to <hi>This</hi> or <hi>That</hi> Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Case,</hi> or <hi>Tryal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was no hard matter for Him to Impose upon <hi>Publick Justice,</hi> for a <hi>Tryal,</hi> Two or Three, before he was known, and before he had laid himself open to the World, in so many <hi>Absurdities,</hi> and <hi>Incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> in <hi>Print:</hi> But since that gross Discovery of his <hi>Impudence,</hi> and <hi>Folly,</hi> He hath <hi>Printed</hi> himself quite out of his <hi>Title, Dignity,</hi> and <hi>Credit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reader</hi> is desir'd also to take further notice, That it is not the <hi>Question</hi> of these <hi>Papers,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther OATES spoke any thing <hi>True,</hi> or <hi>Not?</hi> But the <hi>Impossibility</hi> of Reconciling some <hi>Passages</hi> that do here occur, and the high <hi>Improbability</hi> of many Others, which is here recommended to the Impartial Consideration of all lovers of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Justice.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:201976:2"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN Titus &amp; the Doctor.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
               <p>VErily; sincerely; In the presence of God and Man; as I am a <hi>Minister of the Gospel,</hi> and <hi>Saviour of the Nation;</hi> I think I must leave the Town. <hi>In verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> Our affairs go down the wind extremely. The <hi>Pope, Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits,</hi> joyn'd to the <hi>French-Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, Yorkists, Court-Magistrates,</hi> and <hi>Church of England-men,</hi> have so stupify'd the people, that none (<hi>(except some politick Citizens)</hi>) but can quietly go to bed, without searching their bed-straw for <hi>Fire-balls,</hi> or so much as dreaming their Throats will be cut with <hi>Consecrated Knives,</hi> their Brains knock'd out with <hi>Black-Bills,</hi> and their Wives and Children transported to <hi>Compostella</hi> by <hi>Spanish Pilgrims,</hi> before morning.</p>
               <p>The time was, when we could have Imprison'd, Hang'd drawn and Quarter'd, whom we pleas'd, though never so Innocent, and for what We pleas'd, though never so <hi>impossible</hi> or <hi>absurd,</hi> by Our meer <hi>breath</hi> and <hi>kiss of a Book;</hi> not a Man, from the highest to the lowest, daring openly so much as to question Our <hi>Veracity,</hi> under pain of forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Reputation,</hi> and <hi>Fortune,</hi> if not his Life, by the force of Our <hi>Affidavit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (alass!) <hi>The case is alter'd;</hi> Either the Devil, or <hi>King of Poland</hi> or <hi>Both, (I will not be positive)</hi> have left us in the lurch; Every one sees through Us; Nay, <hi>(So help me God)</hi> stick not, in plain terms, to call us, <hi>bloody perjur'd Villain; Monster of Nature; plague of Our Conntry; Detestation of Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Horrour of Man-kind.</hi> Well, there will come a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and then—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>And <hi>then,</hi> or <hi>before,</hi> we shall doubtless receive a Reward proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to our merit. Prithee what can we hope from any <hi>honest Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly?</hi> We have shamefully abus'd the Authority of the Nation; We have sacrilegiously violated all Divine and Humane Laws; We have provok'd both God and Man to the utmost Vengeance. What can we rely on? 'Tis a wonder the very Earth doth not open, and swallow Us alive. We have long abjur'd all Goodness; We have strugl'd hard with something within us, to shake off and abolish the dreadful Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Belief of a Deity, a Judge, an Eternity, engraven in our Soul, 'Tis true, (alass!) we have found those <hi>Characters</hi> indeleble. Our <hi>Sacriledge;</hi> Our Lusts; Our innumerable <hi>Villanies,</hi> in despight of our hearts, pursue us. The <hi>Blood of Innocents;</hi> The <hi>Cries of Orphans;</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:201976:3"/>The <hi>hideous guilt of blackest Crimes</hi> flie in our face, cleave to our very Entrails, and whether we will or no, render us in a manner <hi>Devils to our selves:</hi> And happy it were, if (like <hi>true Fiends</hi>) we only carried <hi>Hell in our Bosoms;</hi> But our Folly hath at last betray'd us to <hi>publick Infamy;</hi> As thou say'st, <hi>Every one now sees through us:</hi> And like Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>Cain,</hi> we bear about us Marks for all humane Creatures to know us by. In short, <hi>The Gallows groans for us,</hi> and it is Thou hast utterly ruin'd both <hi>Thy self</hi> and <hi>Me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us a while debate the matter seriously: What a strange height of arrogance was it in thee, to swear Me <hi>Doctor of Salamanca?</hi> as if thou hadst on purpose design'd to render my <hi>Stupidity</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> a Testimony of <hi>Perjury.</hi> Why, thou know'st I was never at <hi>Salamanca</hi> in all my life; nor doth that famous
<note n="*" place="margin">See the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanca</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Observator.</hi>
                  </note> University use to admit of such <hi>Blockheads</hi> as Me to so high a <hi>Degree.</hi> Thou might'st have remembred whil'st I was at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> the very Boys derided me for my <hi>sottish Dulness;</hi> Yet I, forsooth, must be <hi>Doctor of Salamanca.</hi> Hadst thou sworn me <hi>Muphti to the Emperour of Morocco,</hi> it might have strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my <hi>Evidence</hi> against Mr. <hi>Elliot:</hi> But (alass!) neither my <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> nor <hi>Behaviour</hi> hath any coherence with a <hi>Christian-Clergy-man.</hi> What could this <hi>sham</hi> of thine conduce to our Invention of the <hi>Plot?</hi> Thou might'st easily have forseen, thy folly herein would make us ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to the Scholars and Students of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge:</hi> Nay, thou could'st not imagine but that the <hi>long Gown</hi> and <hi>Scarf</hi> would give people an occasion to enquire more narrowly into our <hi>scandalous Life.</hi> What canst thou say for thy self? Art not asham'd to let thy <hi>Pride</hi> thus over-run thy <hi>Wit?</hi> Now must I (scorn'd and rejected by all men of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Honesty</hi>) turn <hi>Holder-forth,</hi> and exercise my <hi>Letchery, Riot, Forgery</hi> and <hi>Impudence in a short Cassock</hi> at <hi>Carolina,</hi> and this too at an <hi>under, rate,</hi> and all through thy <hi>Doctorship Sir-Reverence,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is like the rest of thy tricks: Thy arrogance is such, thou canst not contain thy self within any limits or compass. Who but a <hi>Mad-man</hi> would have fallen foul upon his best Friends? Thou hast vomited out thy spleen, in despight (as I may say) of <hi>Truth, Sense, Gratitude,</hi> and <hi>good Manners,</hi> upon the very Persons that first created and supported thee in the <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Evidence.</hi> By my troth, I begin to suspect the <hi>Devil</hi> hath got so entire a possession of thy Heart and Mouth, thou art longer thine own Master. What if our present Patrons the <hi>Whigs</hi> should forsake us; Or what if They themselves should miscarry (as is much to be feared they will) in their Design of a <hi>Commonwealth?</hi> What course wilt thou take? Whither wilt thou go? <hi>Scotland</hi> is now clear of the <hi>Cargilites,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> is already over-stock'd with the <hi>loathsom V rmin</hi> of our <hi>Trade:</hi> Nor is there a Nation in <hi>Europe,</hi> whom the rancour of thy Calumny hath not provok'd to execute Justice on Thee. See therefore to what thou art come: For my part, I tell thee plainly, if I be forc'd to extremeties, I will follow the example of my Fore-father <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>Hang my self.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus</speaker>
               <p>Thou think'st now to silence me, by crying <hi>Rogue</hi> first; but that will not do: Since thou art so hot, I am resolv'd thou shalt hear of some of <hi>thy miscarriages.</hi> Come, answer me directly, there is no <hi>shuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling</hi> or <hi>lying</hi> will serve the turn between <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Me;</hi> Hadst thou
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:201976:3"/>not the best advice Dr. <hi>Tonge</hi> and others could afford thee, towards the <hi>cunning Contrivance</hi> of our <hi>Plot</hi> at <hi>Lambeth</hi> in <hi>August</hi> 1678? was it nor again and again modell'd and revis'd by Persons of a <hi>higher station?</hi> was ever <hi>Bear-whelp</hi> lick'd over with greater diligence, to bring it into shape? hadst thou not all the <hi>Assistance</hi> and <hi>Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> thy very Heart could wish? Did not the <hi>Papists</hi> lie under a <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest prejudice?</hi> were they not despoiled of all ways or means of vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating their <hi>Innocence,</hi> otherwise than by a <hi>(morally impossible)</hi> Proof of a <hi>Negative?</hi> In fine, was there any thing left to thee, but <hi>bare Swearing</hi> and <hi>Impudence?</hi> Notwithstanding all which <hi>advantages helps, props</hi> and <hi>instructions,</hi> what shame and confusion hath thy rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and exorbitance brought upon our heads! Thou hast foisted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>Evidence</hi> such <hi>incredible Fables,</hi> such gross and <hi>palpable Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> such enormous <hi>obvions Forgeries,</hi> such <hi>absolute Impossibilities</hi> such <hi>irreconcilable Circumstances,</hi> such <hi>impracticable Chymoera's,</hi> such <hi>heaps of Non-sence</hi> and <hi>Absurdities,</hi> that the whole World, <hi>Papists, Protestants, Friends</hi> and <hi>Foes,</hi> cry out upon Us, with amazement and horrour.</p>
               <p>For instance: How unluckily hast thou tim'd thy <hi>Plot!</hi> How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towardly circumstanc'd it!
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Staffords Mem.</hi>
                  </note> The whole body of <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> amongst whom, many at least are acknowledg'd and experienc'd by the <hi>best of Protestants</hi> to be men of <hi>Worth, Prudence, Virtue,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemish'd Reputation:</hi> These must be engag'd by <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> in a <hi>Design</hi> so <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>Execrable,</hi> that God and Nature abhor to think on it: They must hazard their <hi>Estates,</hi> their <hi>Families,</hi> their <hi>Bodies,</hi> their <hi>Souls,</hi> their <hi>All,</hi> in an Enterprize so desperate and sot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish, that none but <hi>Mad-men</hi> would <hi>Attempt</hi> it, and nothing less than a <hi>Miracle</hi> could effect it; And this too at a time when they had no reason or motive to seek a change; They must kill the <hi>King,</hi> by whose <hi>merciful Indulgence</hi> they liv'd in peace. They must wade through Bloud, to an uncertain <hi>Liberty</hi> which they already sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyed. <hi>They</hi> must overthrow the Government, for the Re-esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of <hi>which,</hi> they so frankly and unanimously, in the <hi>late Wars,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed their Lives and Fortunes. How could'st thou imagine these <hi>monstrous Impostuers</hi> should long find credit?</p>
               <p>Then again, what <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi> hast thou muster'd into <hi>Thy Plot?</hi> Those very
<note n="*" place="margin">Narrat</note>
                  <hi>Nobelmen,</hi> who, above almost all others, had signaliz'd their <hi>Loyalty</hi> in the Service and Defence both of <hi>This</hi> and <hi>the late King;</hi> and who now, through Age and Infirmities, were retir'd from publick business, and weary of the World; <hi>These</hi> must be the <hi>grand actors</hi> in thy Roguish Conspiracy. Why man, suppose these <hi>Peers</hi> had been really engag'd in a <hi>Trayterous Design:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> who can believe that they would descend so low as to converse with, much less reveal deep and dangerous Secrets to <hi>such Scoundrels as Thee?</hi> Indeed being, as thou wert, wholly ignorant both of the Affairs and true Genius of any <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> of worth, thou hast been so prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterously rash and stupid, as to impose upon several Persons several Offices and Dignities directly <hi>Opposite</hi> and <hi>Repugnant</hi> to their several Qualifications. <hi>One,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Narrat.</note>
                  <hi>because he could seldom go, stand, or feed himself,</hi> must be a <hi>General; Others, because they had never seen a Battel, or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Campaign,</hi> must be <hi>Lieutenant, Major,</hi> and <hi>Commissary-Generals;</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:201976:4"/>A <hi>Third, because an ill Accomptant,</hi> must be general <hi>Pay-master; Some</hi> again, <hi>because they were never train'd up in Warfare, nor so much as ever trail'd a</hi> Pike, must be <hi>Captains, Colonels,</hi> and chief <hi>Commanders</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Nay, the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> a regular sort of <hi>Popish Clergy,</hi> they must sign, seal and deliver Commissions for Military Imployments; And though all men of Reading, Travel or Sense know the <hi>Josuits</hi> to be by their Vow and institute incapable of Prelacy, yet must <hi>They</hi> likewise (together with others whose Talents entitled them to nothing but their <hi>Beads</hi>) be enrolled in the List of thy <hi>English Bishops.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">o Ibidem.</note> How is it possible these gross Fopperies of thine should not at last come out? This it is to attempt a Villany, and want Brains to accomplish it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>What tell'st thou me of mistiming, misplacing, and wrong circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancing of things, contrary to known Practice, Vows, and Institutes? Didst not thou positively swear, That
<note n="*" place="margin">At their several Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Mr. <hi>Gowen</hi> Mr. <hi>Preston,</hi> and others, known by all their Neighbours to be ancient House-keepers and Married-men; Didst not thou, I say, swear, in express contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the acknowledged Practice, and Laws of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> That they were Priests; And that thou hadst seen them say <hi>Mass,</hi> administer the <hi>Sacraments, &amp;c.</hi> in the publick Chappels; Didst thou not also swear, That <hi>John Smith</hi> (likewise a Married-man) was <hi>a Lay brother of the Order of the Politiciani,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Narrat</note> (an Order in the Moon, out of which this <hi>strange Lay-brother</hi> dropt down hither; for all the world knows <hi>there is no such Order in the</hi> Roman Church.) By a like contrivance thou mad'st
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Twelve <hi>Benedictine Monks, Canons of Windsor,</hi> whom thou might'st as wisely have made <hi>Knights of the Garter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now thou putst me in mind of preposterous Timing, Naming and Circumstancing:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Irelands</hi> Tryal.</note> Could'st thou find none whereon to fix the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>King,</hi> but harmless <hi>Pickering;</hi> a man <hi>so remarkably Meek and Innoffensive,</hi> he would not have killed a <hi>Mouse;</hi> A Man <hi>who was never so hardy as to let off a Pistol, or handle any other weapon than his Needle;</hi> He (forsooth) must be the Person design'd for the desperate horrid Action of Killing His Majesty, <hi>by the loud shot of a large Gun; In the open day; In the midst of His Courtiers; In the publick Park.</hi> This grand Engineer, on whose Military Skill and Artifice depended the whole Machine of the <hi>Plot,</hi> had indeed a <hi>Silver Bullet</hi> (in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaisance, it seems to the <hi>King</hi>) but was still at a loss in his other <hi>Imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for the Fact; Sometimes the Flint of his Gun was loose; Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there was no Powder in the Pan; and so he continually missed his aim, for which he must (like a <hi>School-boy</hi>) be whipt, and lastly, have <hi>Thirty Thousand Masses, (when he was Hang'd)</hi> said for his Hire. Is not this pleasant matter to be brought before an High Court of Justice, against the Life of an <hi>Innocent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such-another of thy Inventions is that of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi>'s Poysoning, and the <hi>four Ruffians</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wakem</hi>'s Tryal.</note> stabbing the <hi>King.</hi> Sir <hi>George</hi> must have 15000 <hi>l.</hi> in all, and 5000 <hi>l.</hi> in hand for his share; but the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen-Russians</hi> (tho' most of them <hi>Persons of Quality</hi>) could only be allowed each Twenty Guineys, sent them by <hi>Coleman</hi> to <hi>Windsor</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here also mark how palpably thou hast betray'd thy own Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guery. Thou positively swor'st, Thou never wast
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staff</hi>'s Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>Really</hi> a <hi>Roman
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:201976:4"/>Catholick,</hi> but only <hi>feign'd</hi> thy self to be so, on purpose to discover <hi>Popish Intrigues,</hi> and by that means <hi>Save His Majesty</hi> from other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inevitable Death and Destruction; Yet (see thy prodigious Impudence!
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs.</note> at the same time, and with the same breath, thou ownedst thou wert conscious for above a year together of the daily Attempts made by <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> to shoot the <hi>King;</hi> Thou hourly expectedst for several Months the horrid effects of Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi>'s <hi>Poison;</hi> Thou wert privy to the design'd Assassination at <hi>Windsor;</hi> Thou knew'st the <hi>Ruffians</hi> were actually upon the place, and ready for the Villany; Thou sawst the Guineys sent them for their Encouragement, and every moment waitedst to her the fatal Blow was given: Nevertheless thy <hi>Watchful Eye, Loyal Care, Holy Zeal</hi> and <hi>Tender Conscience</hi> would not let thee make a Discovery, though (thou said'st) thou knew'st for certain, the Gun was already even at the <hi>King</hi>'s Breast; the Cup of Poison at his Lip, and the Daggers almost at his very Heart: Yet thou never criedst out, <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Lord's Anointed;</hi> never calledst for immediate Succour; never warnedst the <hi>King</hi> of His eminent Danger; never divertedst the Impending Mischief, nor so much as opendst thy mouth to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close any of these horrid Treasons, until such time as the <hi>King</hi> might have been kill'd a thousand times over. What can judicious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons think of this? Will they not say, Had thy Stories been true, thou might'st and ought'st to have taken the Criminals with their Tools about them: To have caused <hi>Pickering</hi> with his <hi>Gun,</hi> and the <hi>Ruffians</hi> with their <hi>Daggers</hi> in their hands, to be seized; Thus thou had'st discharged a good Conscience; Sav'd the <hi>King</hi>'s Life, and given some proof of thy prodigious Evidence: But, as matters stand, thou hast demonstratively convinc'd the world, Thou art ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Execrable Villain, in <hi>Swearing</hi> such things, or worse, in so long <hi>concealing them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>There was a necessity for me to nominate some particular persons, else those who modell'd our <hi>Plot</hi> for us, could not have put it into right shape; and I not knowing any body amongst the <hi>Papists</hi> likely to commit such horrid Crimes, named at <hi>random</hi> those who first came to my mind. But Thou, as if on purpose to make all <hi>Europe,</hi> by the knowledge of its own Innocence, experimental Witnesses of thy <hi>Perjury,</hi> hast Impeach'd by whole-sale, and pronounced Universally Guilty of the PLOT, most or all <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Narr.</note> both Princes and People, not only of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> but also of <hi>France, Italy, Spain, Portugal, Germany, Flanders,</hi> &amp;c. (an Affront and Scandal to almost all <hi>Christendom.</hi> Now tell me, Is it possible that any in their senses should long believe,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staffords</hi> Memoirs.</note> that amongst so many Thousands of <hi>both Sexes,</hi> of <hi>several Nations,</hi> of <hi>different Interests,</hi> of <hi>all sorts, states</hi> and <hi>conditions,</hi> as must necessarily have been privy to, and Partners in thy pretended Massacres, Treasons and Villanies, none should have any remorse for so Bloudy, so Unnatural and Detestable a Wickedness; None Worth, Wit or Grace to reveal it; No inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Accident; No conviction of Judgment; No levity of Mind; No change of Religion; No Temporal Advantage; No Friendship, or Relation; No disagreement of Parties, happen to detect it, for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:201976:5"/>divers years together, till at last Thou, and after Thee, thy other Companions, <hi>Bedloe, Dugdale, Dangerfield,</hi> &amp;c. (the Scum and Refuse of Mankind, rak'd out of Goals, Whipt, Pillory'd, and one way or other branded with Infamy,) made this grand discovery, (good Men!) out of tenderness of Conscience? Is it possible, I say, that any in their Senses should believe this?</p>
               <p>Then, to second these incredible Lies with greater, thou inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedst huge formidable Armies, composed of
<note n="*" place="margin">Narr.</note> 20000 <hi>Presbyterian Scots;</hi> 40000 <hi>Wild Irish;</hi> 20000 <hi>English Papists,</hi> substantial Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men, in the very City of <hi>London;</hi> a proportionable number in other Counties, the Total, by Computation, amounting to a matter of Two or Three hundred Thousand, Horse, Foot and Dragoons, some <hi>above,</hi> some <hi>under</hi> ground, (besides <hi>Spanish Pilgrims,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>French, Flemish,</hi> and other Foreign Confederates) equipped and ready, most of them within 24
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> hours, and all of them within less than ten days time, for immediate Service. These vast Swarms (thou tell'st us) were provided with correspondent Stores of
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. 5 <hi>Jes.</hi> Try.</note>
                  <hi>Ammunition, Weapons, Black-Bills, Fire-Balls, Granadoe-shells, Daggers, Screw'd-Guns, Mortar pieces,</hi> &amp;c. Now then thou could'st not imagine but that the <hi>King</hi>'s Officers, (unless diverted by the Incredibility of thy <hi>Fables</hi>) would make diligent search where these Millions of Men, and Mountains of Magazines were: And that, not finding, either by thy directions, or their own scrutiny, the least Foot-steps of any such thing, it must needs bring an unavoidable confusion to our Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; Especially seeing all men knew it was impossible these huge Armies and Armouries could be invisibly dispers'd, or convey'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, upon so sudden and unexpected a Discovery, made in the very nick of time when (thou pretendedst) they were to have been used.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Well, and was thy Impudence less, when thou expresly sworest thou hadst seen
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Memoirs.</note> some Hundreds, and deliver'dst with thine own hands not a few, of Commissions for all Military-Offices, as,
<note n="*" place="margin">Narr.</note>
                  <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, Adjutant, Advocate-Generals,</hi> &amp;c. Divers Patents granted for Dignities of State, as
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>Chancellor, Treasurer,</hi> &amp;c. all Signed and Sealed <hi>(O Ridiculous!)</hi> by the General of the Jesuits: Many Bulls and Briefs for Ecclesiastical Preferments, and numberless Volumes of Letters and Pacquets, containing Damnable Treasons, of all which thou knew'st the exact Dates, and could'st tell, when, and where read, to, and from whom writ and directed; Not only so, but thou could'st recite upon thy Fingers-ends the express words of almost every Letter. Nay, thou hadst the confidence <hi>(though a Leud, Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly, Cashier'd Blockhead, and a Vagabond)</hi> to affirm thou hadst a
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Patent of thy own, authorizing thee to be a Grand Councellor in Civil, Military, and Ecclesiastical Affairs.</p>
               <p>Now, could'st thou not fore-see the Papists would incessantly cry out [
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Memoirs.</note>
                  <hi>Let him produce</hi> One single Commission, One Patent, Bull, Brief, or so much as a Scrip of Paper, <hi>signed as he pretends; Let him bring</hi> some Umbrage of Reason or Argument, distinct from his <hi>Bare Swearing;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">5 <hi>Jesuits</hi> Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>There were</hi> many Thousands of Letters, <hi>together with</hi> seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bonds, Bills and Writings, for considerable Sums of Money, <hi>seized</hi> on a sudden <hi>in the Chambers and Closets of the</hi> Conspirators:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:201976:5"/>
                  <hi>Now,</hi> if these Men were not surprized, Why did they not save their Indentures and Treasures? <hi>But,</hi> if they were, How could they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve their Treasonable Papers?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Plotters, (if what <hi>Oates</hi> swears be True) <hi>were not very Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or</hi> shie of their Secrets: <hi>And indeed</hi> it is wholly Impossible, <hi>in</hi> such a Conjuncture of Circumstances, such a Multiplicity of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions, Bulls, Letters, <hi>&amp;c. but some</hi> Original Writing <hi>should be extant, and forth-coming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why did not this</hi> Oates, <hi>this</hi> Man of Trust and Intrigue, <hi>produce at least</hi> That
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Patent he said he had to be of the Grand Consult? <hi>It would have been</hi> of mighty Force to strengthen his Testimony. <hi>Why did he not immediately carry to the</hi> King, Councel, or some Magistrate, <hi>whilst it was in his Custody,</hi> That Damnable Paper or
<note n="*" place="margin">5 <hi>Jesuits</hi> Tryal.</note> Instrument <hi>drawn up</hi> (as he said) <hi>at the</hi> White-Horse-Tavern, wherein the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates stood engag'd to pursue the Murther of the <hi>King? Which</hi> Paper, <hi>he saith, He himself carried from</hi> Club <hi>to</hi> Club: <hi>And saw, and</hi> procur'd it to be sign'd by each respective Conspirator under his own hand. <hi>This would have been an</hi> Undeniable Evidence; <hi>Especially, produc'd by a Person who made it his business</hi> to discover a <hi>Plot, and</hi> save the <hi>King</hi>'s Life.] But because (as thou well know'st) there was not any thing of Truth in what thou swor'st, nor by consequence could be any thing of solid Proof to make it out: the conclusion at last, though after much mischief and <hi>Blood-shed,</hi> must needs be Fatal to us Both.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>Were not thy <hi>Chymoera's</hi> as absurd, and in all points as pernicious to us as Mine? Didst thou not in express terms swear, the <hi>Jesuits</hi> became <hi>True-Protestant-Holders-forth,</hi> and preach'd Sedition and Treason in <hi>Presbyterian Conventicles?</hi> Never fore-seeing or regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that when the Government had once found out our Impostures, and accordingly discarded us, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were of all others most likely to become (as now they are) our main Support and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Mark the effects of thy Rashness herein; These very <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> are now search'd, as the <hi>Nests of Jesuits,</hi> and <hi>Nurseries of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion;</hi> Our present Friends disturb'd in their <hi>Religious Cheats,</hi> and their <hi>real Designs, Associations,</hi> and <hi>Treacheries,</hi> discover'd and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, through thy Shams and Fictions.</p>
               <p>Nay, on my Conscience, (if I had any) a body would suspect thou thy self art a <hi>Conventicling Emissary</hi> of the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> set on by them, on purpose to embroil the Three Kingdoms, to fix an Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my upon the face of Justice, and render the Mame of <hi>Protestant</hi> odious to all Nations.</p>
               <p>Such another Foppery was that of thy swearing, The <hi>Jesuits</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Narra.</note> had 60000 <hi>l.</hi> a year, and 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in bank, out of which they made 50 <hi>l. per cent</hi> Interest; And that they practiced in <hi>London</hi> the Trades of <hi>Merchants, Tobacconists, Goldsmiths, Scriv'ners,</hi> &amp;c. which Trades they engrossed to themselves and Partners in so high a degree, as to gain an exact estimate of the Riches and Strength of the whole Nation. Now, into what a strange <hi>praemunire</hi> hast thou here brought the City? If the <hi>Jesuits</hi> can, and do (as thou saist) upon occasion profess themselves <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and at the same time
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:201976:6"/>likewise exercise the above-named beneficial Trades: Who knows but all, or most of the <hi>Presbyterian Merchants, Scriv'ners</hi> and <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> (for Example, <hi>Bethel, Player, Pilkington, Ward, Wilmore,</hi>) are really <hi>Jesuits?</hi> Why may not the <hi>King (if He will believe thy Testimony)</hi> upon just grounds seize on the Persons and Effects of all the <hi>Presbyterian Citizens,</hi> (who now maintain Thee) as <hi>suspected Traytors,</hi> and <hi>Managers of the</hi> Plot? Especially, seeing thou swor'st a Dangerous Matter, (though a Lie at both ends) That there were as many
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> as might suffice to cut the Throats of 100000 <hi>Protestants</hi> in it. Now, where and how should people imagine these invisible Swarms of <hi>Papists</hi> could he shrowded and hid, if not under the masque of <hi>Protestant Dissenters?</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, no mortal Man can can give a Reason why thy present Patrons the <hi>Dissenters</hi> are not <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Jesuits</hi> now, as well as they were when (according to thy Evidence) <hi>They</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Preface</hi> to the Narrat.</note>
                  <hi>brought His late Sacred Majesty's Head to the Block.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Why might not I turn the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> into <hi>Jesuits,</hi> as well as thou hast metamorphosed the same <hi>Jesuits</hi> into <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-men?</hi> The <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Interest</hi> of the <hi>Jesuits</hi> are much consonant to the <hi>One</hi> as the <hi>Other;</hi> The probability of Complotting dangerous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues; The Trust and Fidelity in keeping each others Secrets; The advantage to be gain'd by Success, (to wit, <hi>mutual Destruction</hi>) are likewise the same. Yet thou positively swor'st, That
<note n="*" place="margin">Narra.</note> Mr. <hi>Strange, Grey,</hi> and other <hi>Jesuits,</hi> meeting with one <hi>Green,</hi> and Eight more <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-men,</hi> at <hi>Puddle-Dock,</hi> and first closing together in <hi>Doctrinal Points,</hi> they at length combined in a Damnable Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>Firing the City.</hi> And mark thy notable Policy here; These <hi>Fire-Merchants</hi> (as thou call'st them) must be assisted by 50 or 60 <hi>Irish,</hi> and several <hi>French,</hi> (besides the above-mention'd <hi>Jesuitical Trades-men,</hi> who thus became Incendiaries to their own Houses,) They must be furnished with <hi>Magazines of monstrous Fire-works</hi> in
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid,</note>
                  <hi>Granadoe-shells,</hi> and Thousands of <hi>Fire-balls,</hi> of which 700 were made use on, (though no Reliques or Footsteps of any such <hi>Machines</hi> or <hi>Balls,</hi> upon sedulous enquiry, ever had been, or could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.) During the <hi>Conflagration,</hi> multitudes of Men and Women, <hi>(privy to the Secret)</hi> must be employed to ransack and plunder the City, and carry the Spoil of
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Cloth, Plate, Boxes and Bundles, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to certain Ware-houses in <hi>Wild-street</hi> and <hi>Somerset-house, (though no such Persons were ever discovered, nor any such Goods or Ware-houses ever known.</hi>) Amongst other Booties, they got at one clap, and of one Man, no less than
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 1000 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>haracts of Diamonds,</hi> which were afterwards sold for 3500 <hi>l. (though none ever yet either complained he lost, or owned he had any such Jewels.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all this while (as the <hi>Devil</hi> would have it.) thou never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membredst what thou hadst immediately before expresly sworn, <hi>(viz.) That the main Drift and Design of the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Jesuits <hi>and</hi> Fifth-monarchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>in burning the City, was, during the Combustion, to Murder the</hi> King, <hi>and make a general Insurrection.</hi> Now, who will believe the <hi>Jesuits</hi> would busie themselves, and imploy multitudes of the their Proselytes in pilfering of Cloaths, Boxes and Lumber, just in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:201976:6"/>very nick of time, when they were <hi>to kill the King; to rise in open Rebellion; to cut all the Protestants Throats; to enslave Three Nations,</hi> and manage <hi>an Army of at least Two or Three hundred Thousand Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, if the <hi>Jesuits</hi> intended to <hi>kill the King,</hi> &amp;c. How came they to let slip <hi>so favourable an advantage?</hi> Why did they let fall their Design? A body would think <hi>They could never hope for a fairer oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. The City was burning; Its Government relaxed; The People all in consternation; The King amongst them; and nothing seem'd wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to compleat their Enterprize:</hi> Yet after all, <hi>no Murder, no Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, no Rebellion, no Disturbance</hi> ensued. What will wise Men from hence conclude, but <hi>that the Fire it self was an effect of God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And the pretended Murder, Treason, Rebellion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the meer product of thy Villanous Brain?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>But I put a <hi>Salvo</hi> to that Objection, by saying,
<note n="*" place="margin">Narrat</note>
                  <hi>The Jesuits were not then secure of the Duke,</hi> who about that time was but a well-wisher to them. Besides, <hi>They seeing the King so industrious in extinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fire, could not find in their hearts to kill him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Worse and worse; Why should the <hi>Jesuits</hi> attempt a Design be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were ready for it? Why should they begin an Enterprize which they already knew ought not to be pursued? Did the <hi>Jesuits</hi> set fire to the City, and in the midst of the Flames bethink themselves whether the <hi>Duke</hi> were secure to them, and whether they had taken right measures, or no? Oh! but <hi>They could not find in their hearts to kill the King, when they saw him so busie in putting out the Fire.</hi> Mark the inconsistence of thy <hi>Perjuries.</hi> Didst thou not frequently swear, That the <hi>Jesuits</hi> accounted it an high Act of Virtue, and meritorious of Heaven, to murder an <hi>Heretick,</hi> especially the <hi>King?</hi> That they determined, without Pity or Remorse, to cut the Throats of all, even the most Innocent Protestants in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> That they used to Consecrate Swords, Knives and Daggers for such purposes? That they looked upon the King as a
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>Bastard,</hi> and <hi>Traytor to the Pope,</hi> and chief obstacle to their Pretences? That therefore they encourag'd and hir'd some to <hi>shoot Him,</hi> some to <hi>poison Him,</hi> some to <hi>stab Him,</hi> &amp;c? And lastly, That they fir'd the City on purpose to gain an opportunity to <hi>take him off,</hi> (as thou term'dst it.) But now, when these merciless <hi>Jesuits</hi> had him in their Clutches, ready for the Slaughter, and all their Confederates wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the Blow: just then <hi>(O miracle!)</hi> comes a qualm of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness upon them, and <hi>they could not find in their hearts to kill him.</hi> Why? <hi>Because he endeavoured to quench the Fire which they themselves had kindled, on purpose to destroy him.</hi> This is fine stuff, is it not think'st thou? and a worthy Subject for an Inscription on the <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>If my Sham of the <hi>Papists Firing the City</hi> was absurd and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Thy Figments of <hi>Firing Southwark,</hi> and <hi>Burning the Navy,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Narra.</note> were no less ridiculous and non-sensical; So there's a double <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for thy <hi>Oliver.</hi> And now give ear to other matters of the same Leaven: Didst thou not swear, That one
<note n="*" place="margin">Narr.</note>
                  <hi>John Smith,</hi> a Porter or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:201976:7"/>Letter-Carrier, <hi>(a fit Person for a Minister of State)</hi> gave <hi>Intelligence</hi> to the King of <hi>France,</hi> of all our <hi>King</hi>'s Intrigues and Policies; How he stood affected for <hi>Peace</hi> or <hi>War,</hi> and what daily passed in the <hi>Cabinet Councel, (whereby surely this State-Interloper engrossed all the Trade from the</hi> French-Pensioners) for which also he had (as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proportionable to the Grandeur and Importance of his Office) no less than 500 <hi>l. per annum?</hi> Dist thou not likewise swear, It was plotted by the <hi>Jesuits,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> The <hi>Emperour</hi> should be told, That the King of <hi>England</hi> (abounding in Money) had sent under-hand great Sums to the <hi>Hungarian Rebels</hi> to go on <hi>(as an encouragement, it seems, for his own Subjects to do the like,)</hi> in their Rebelion; And that a <hi>Latine-Letter,</hi> importing thus much, was sent by a <hi>Lay-Brother, (a proper Embassador)</hi> to the <hi>Emperour?</hi> Didst thou not moreover swear, That <hi>Twelve</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>English Jesuits</hi> were sent into <hi>Holland,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>Flemish Jesuits</hi> were not so well known, and capable of acting Treason in their own Country) to inform the <hi>Dutch</hi> (those States being wholly guided and influenced by the said <hi>Jesuits</hi>) That the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> would make himself King over them. Besides,—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Stop a little, and take some of thy own Farces along with thee. Did thou not swear, That <hi>one Single Jesuit,</hi> and he a * <hi>Spaniard,</hi> had promised 10000 <hi>l.</hi> (which doubtless he never had, nor could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure) for an hire to those that would kill our <hi>King?</hi> And that a <hi>French Jesuit</hi> also (out of a transport of Zeal) had given before-hand the like impossible Sum for the same end? These <hi>Jesuits,</hi> especially Strangers, are wonderful Prodigals of their money.</p>
               <p>Again, Didst thou not swear, That a certain
<note n="*" place="margin">Narrat.</note>
                  <hi>Drummer</hi> had Ten Royals of Eight, for carrying some Treasonable Lettes from St. <hi>Omers</hi> to <hi>Paris?</hi> And one
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
                  <hi>Armstrong</hi> a <hi>Jesuit</hi> had allowed 200 <hi>l.</hi> for the like Portage from <hi>Valadolid</hi> to <hi>Madrid?</hi> (though both these Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries were <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and thou saidst) <hi>Coufederate in the Plot.</hi>) Yet, at the same time, thou affirmedst, These, and innumerable others, the like, or worse Letters, containing in exprss terms the blackest Crimes of Murder and Treason, were daily sent from <hi>London</hi> to St. <hi>Omers, Paris, Madrid,</hi> &amp;c.
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> and from thence also to <hi>London,</hi> and so up and down <hi>England,</hi> (though a <hi>Protestant Country,</hi> and <hi>designed Scene of the Tragedy</hi>) by the Common-Post, some for <hi>Two-pence,</hi> and others at most for <hi>Eight-pence apiece.</hi> Nay, the <hi>Jesuits</hi> were so care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less of their Treasonable Letters, as to
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> carry them about in their Pockets, and drop them in their Walks and Divertisements. Was it not pity, that Thou, their Cabinet-Councellor (forsooth) and then also imperceptibly to them, contriving a Discovery, could'st never find, steal, intercept, or discover so much as <hi>One</hi> of these almost every where obvious Letters? What Inferences, think'st thou, will Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Persons make from these on all sides so inconsistent <hi>Fables?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>Why dost thou object to me the Incongruities of filling the <hi>Post-Offices;</hi> and stuffing mens Chambers and Pockets with invisible Letters of Treason? Thou hast made the <hi>Jesuits</hi> as lavish of their <hi>Tongues,</hi> as I have of their <hi>Pens.</hi> Didst thou not swear, That these <hi>Jesuits (sottish stupid</hi> Jesuits!) were so regardless of their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:201976:7"/>so Mad, Bewich'd, and Infatuated, as to Preach
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Sermons, before a Company of Boys, (who seldom keep Secrets, and who might some of them, at least, for any thing they knew, in time become <hi>Protestants,</hi> and tell all,) <hi>That</hi> Charles Stuart <hi>is no Lawful King, but a Bastard, come of a Spurious Race; And that His Father was a black</hi> Scotch-<hi>man, and not King</hi> Charles <hi>I.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>And that His Majesty's Religion entituled Him to nothing but sudden Death and Destruction?</hi> Nay, thou affirmedst, the <hi>Jesuits</hi> were so strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Impertinent and Non-sensical, as that, notwithstanding they were certain of one anothers knowledge to the contrary, yet, discoursing privately among themselves, they would often, to no manner of purpose, positively averr,
<note n="*" place="margin">Narr.</note>
                  <hi>That</hi> Charles <hi>I. was not King</hi> James<hi>'s Son, but a Bastard, begotten on the Body of</hi> Ann <hi>of</hi> Denmark <hi>by her Tayler; And that this present King was also a Bastard, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to rule by the Sword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this rate also thou swor'st. That
<note n="*" place="margin">Narra.</note> one <hi>Blundel</hi> a <hi>Jesuit</hi> was dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify'd with a Patent of a wonderful Tenor; First, constituting him <hi>Ordinary at Newgate:</hi> his Office there being to Retrieve condemned Thieves and Rogues from the Gallows, on purpose to make them Fellow-Conspirators, and Managers, (for want of <hi>Papists</hi> willing and apt to such Exercises) in burning of Houses, cutting of Throats, and the like wicked and mischievous Designs; Secondly, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing him to keep several <hi>Catechistical Schools</hi> in the City of <hi>London:</hi> where, instead of <hi>receiving,</hi> he was to
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>give</hi> Money, (a <hi>Jesuitical Craft</hi>) to Parents, (being <hi>Protestvnts,</hi> for <hi>Papists</hi> surely needed not to be brib'd) to permit them to teach their Children the <hi>Popish Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret</hi> of <hi>Treason against the Life and Interest of the</hi> King.</p>
               <p>Again, thou imprudently swor'st, That, notwithstanding Mr. <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi> was assuredly inform'd that thou hadst made, both
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> to the King and a Minister of State, <hi>an ample Discovery of all the Plotters Bloody Designs;</hi> Yet <hi>Whitebread,</hi> Instead of running away himself, or advising others his Confederates to do so,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> ordered thee (for sureness to find him) to come to his Chamber; and there the pettish old Man (as if he had a mind to hang Himself and Friends, by irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one at whose Mercy they lay, and who had already abandoned them,) fell on chiding and beating thee, (poor Child) giving thee three blows with his Cane, and a box on the Ear; After which, <hi>(O Wonderful!)</hi> this <hi>Whitebread</hi> and his Companions still continued so supinely negligent of their own Safety, so regardless of the Affront given, and what might follow this Bastinadoe: that they not only remained in their several Lodgings, (when a body would think it had been more than high time to have betaken themselves to their heels) but one of them, two days after, doubtless to help out thy <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi>) told thee,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>Coniers</hi> was gone to <hi>Windsor</hi> to stab the King. Are not these likely Stories?</p>
               <p>But then, for thy quaint Devices of <hi>C. R. R. C. Black-boy, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-tree-Will, Barley-broth, Mum, Chocolat, Order of Magpies, Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals of Sheeps Fat, Tormentilio's,</hi> and <hi>Tewxbury-Mustard-balls:</hi> These indeed are so Sublime Notions, such Quintessences of Wit and Art, that nothing under the Degree of <hi>Doctor of Salamanca</hi> could either invent or understand them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:201976:8"/>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>What a clutter thou keep'st about a few <hi>Peccadilio's</hi> whilst I have still heaps of monstrous Contradictions and Perjuries to lay to thy charge. People a long time, some out of Zeal, others out of Policy; some out of deference to Higher Powers, and the rest following the Stream, without examining <hi>why?</hi> or <hi>wherefore?</hi> gave implicite Faith to whatever thou imposedst on them; And might have done so still, had not thy Folly, transported by success, become so Rampant and Audacious, that no Bounds or Limits could hold thee. Didst thou not, in the House of Lords,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stafford's</hi> Tryal.</note> upon mature Deliberation, positively swear, <hi>Thou hadst now wholly discharged thy Conscience, and declared all thou knew'st against any Person or Persons, of what Degree or Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity soever in</hi> England? Yet afterwards, finding encouragement, and precipitated by malice, Didst thou not, <hi>in the same House of Lords,</hi> with an unparallell'd Insolence, accuse our <hi>Gracious</hi> Queen <hi>of most Damnable High-Treason?</hi> What, in the Devil's Name, made thee thus to <hi>Contradict and Perjure thy self,</hi> so publickly and palpably, in the very Presence, and to the Face of so Honourable an Assembly? Could'st thou not see, (besotted Miscreant) <hi>That the Transcendent Lustre of the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staffords</hi> Memoirs.</note> Queens <hi>Virtue, Innocence, and endeared Affection to His Majesty, leaves no place for Calumny to fix upon? And that the bare charge of so foul a Crime, upon so Renowned a Goodness, is of it self, Independent of other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontradictions, more then enough to proclaim thee a Villain?</hi> Wretch that thou art! What was it thou proposedst of advantage to thy self by this <hi>more than Sacrilegious Temerity?</hi> What was it thou hopedst from <hi>the Calumniation of an Heroick Princess; In Birth and Fortune; In Courage and Constancy; In Meekness and Patience; Piety and Prudence, Superlatively Great?</hi> What could'st thou discern in the <hi>Fpitome of all the Graces, In the Treasury of all Conjugal Faith and Love, Obnoxious to Obloquy?</hi> Surely thou af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectedst hereby to be reputed in Villainy the Second of Mankind; and to shew all the World, <hi>There could be found amongst Mortals, none, but</hi> Judas <hi>and</hi> Oates, <hi>wicked enough to betray the Life of</hi> Christ <hi>and the</hi> Queen.</p>
               <p>Little less was thy Impudence; Little less the fatal Consequence; Little less thy detestable Villainy, in swearing
<note n="*" place="margin">Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Duke.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Thou saw'st the</hi> Duke <hi>at Mass, through Two or Three several Walls, and as many double Doors, in an Oblique part of a Closet.</hi> Why, in the Name of <hi>Belial,</hi> didst thou give ear to those Malignant Spirits that instigated thee to this Insupportable Arrogance against the Best, and most Accomplished of Princes? What didst thou mean, thus to sham thy own <hi>Plot,</hi> and by Out-swearing all Possibility, to become <hi>an Evidence against thy self?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>Thou shalt get little advantage by rubbing up my old Sores. Dost thou not remember how thou
<note n="*" place="margin">Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition at the <hi>Council.</hi>
                  </note> disownedst (and truly) all personal knowledge of Mr. <hi>Coleman?</hi> And being brought face to face at the Council-Board, at a time too when the Design of the King's Murder, and whole Systeme of the <hi>Plot,</hi> was under examine: Didst thou not there positively assert, <hi>Thou knew'st him not, nor hadst ever seen him before;</hi> No, nor hadst any thing to alledge against him, but certain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:201976:8"/>Fictitious Letters (of thy own framing,) no resemblance of which, upon search, ever appear'd amongst <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Writings? Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, about a month after, when thou perceivedst that Zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; Hatred of Popery; Tenderness for the King's Life, and Danger of their own Throats, had disposed Men (deluded and frighted by thy Fables) to give credit to all thou saidst: Then, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to thy former assertion at the Council, thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedst long and great
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal.</note> intimacy with this same <hi>Coleman.</hi> (Fair, Tall, Don <hi>John</hi> himself was no better known to thee at <hi>Madrid,</hi> then thou wast to <hi>Coleman</hi> at <hi>London.</hi>) Thou chargedst him also,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> to have been privy and aiding to the intended Assassination of His Majesty at <hi>Windsor;</hi> To have consented to the shooting of the King by <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Pickering,</hi> and to the poisoning of Him by Sir <hi>G. Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> To have been at certain Treasonable Consults at the <hi>Savoy</hi> in <hi>August,</hi> (when indeed <hi>Coleman</hi> was in <hi>Warwickshire;</hi>) To have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into <hi>Ireland</hi> 200000 <hi>l.</hi> (stoln, I warrant, by the <hi>Jesuits</hi> at the firing of <hi>London,</hi> and sent over together with the 40000
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>Black-Bills;</hi> From whence else can people imagine so vast a Treasure should arise? or how be privately remitted into <hi>Ireland?</hi> for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on the Rebellion.</p>
               <p>Well; But did not <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters and Writings, containing real matters offensive to the State, and for which he suffer'd, put such a varnish upon my Forgeries, that his
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Projects and my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postures were promiscuously taken for the same thing? Believe me, the finding of those Letters, and the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hills,</hi> &amp;c. Try.</note> Death of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> happening both during the Sessions of a favourable Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were the luckiest Jobbs we ever had, since our first commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Swearing-Masters.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>The more thou stirr'st in defence of thy Villainy, the worse it will stink. Those very
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Memoirs.</note> Writings of <hi>Coleman,</hi> however in themselves offensive to the State, were yet so far from confirming a Plot, such as thou pretendedst to discover, that they directly evince the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; For the whole Subject and Context of the Letters, bear a plain and open face of what the Author designed; And the Writer was a Person so qualified and circumstanced, as that, had there been a Plot, he would in all likelihood have been a main Engine and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver of it; Nevertheless, there is not one single word or syllable in them, from whence may be drawn any rational Inference favourable, but rather, every Period candidly understood, in diameter opposite and destructive to thy <hi>Chymaera's:</hi> The substance of those Letters being only some over-weening Conceits and Policies of an Aspiring Man, willing to be <hi>Great,</hi> or at least to be <hi>thought so;</hi> and desiring, perhaps, in some measure, a <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> without <hi>Confron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> much less <hi>Destroying</hi> the King or Government, as thou wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgedst; wherein also (as far as appears by the Letters) he was no wise seconded by the <hi>Papists in general,</hi> nor much countenanced by those whose favour he seem'd to affect; So that, upon the whole matter, <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Writings, Proclamations and Intrigues, are rather (as is said before a <hi>manifest Vindication of the Papists Innocence,</hi> than any <hi>Proof or Conviction of a Popish-Plot.</hi> In short, what connexion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:201976:9"/>is there between an Universal Combination of all Papists, to Murder the King, to Introduce <hi>French</hi>-Armies, to cut all the Protestant Throats in the Three Kingdoms: And an imaginary fancy of one private Person, to procure the King Money, to work an Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> and dispose the Parliament to a Moderation on account of Religion? The first is the sum of thy <hi>Hellish Plot;</hi> The second, the scope and purport of <hi>Coleman's unwarrantable Writings and Letters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, as for the Death of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey;</hi> Our Brother <hi>Prance</hi> himself (the <hi>Chief Evidence</hi>) hath spoil'd all our
<note n="*" place="margin">On the Annivers. of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs and Pageantry on that score, with his
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hills,</hi> &amp;c. Tryal.</note> many <hi>Self-contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> His <hi>absurd and impossible Circumstances;</hi> His <hi>Imprecations</hi> and <hi>Execrations</hi> over and over before the
<note n="*" place="margin">Deposit. at <hi>Council.</hi>
                  </note> King and Council, <hi>pro &amp; con</hi> to the same thing; His
<note n="*" place="margin">Observat.</note>
                  <hi>Silver-Tankards</hi> and <hi>Brass-Screws;</hi> His <hi>Sham-cauterizing of</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The D's Picture at Guild-hall.</note>
                  <hi>Pictures;</hi> His
<note n="*" place="margin">Observ.</note>
                  <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Blasphemies;</hi> His <hi>Sacraments</hi> and <hi>God-damn-me's.</hi> As if he design'd to render himself Detestable and Infamous, on purpose to make void his Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and clear the Papists of <hi>that Imputation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Now stand fair, and let me be <hi>Plaintiff.</hi> How could it be possible, but that thy <hi>rank Perjuries</hi> should at last be detected: seeing thou didst so desperately run on, without Fear or Wit; never regarding either <hi>Time, Place, Matter, Manner,</hi> or <hi>Persons; when, where, what, how,</hi> or <hi>against whom</hi> thou swor'st? Did'st thou not aver, Thou saw'st Mr. <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Tryal.</note> and held'st Treasonable Discourses with him in <hi>London,</hi> between the 8th. and 12th. of <hi>August</hi> 78. when as no less than Twelve Witnesses, (and, if required, Twelve times that number might have been brought) Persons of unquestionable Worth,
<note place="margin">5. <hi>Jes.</hi> Try.</note> Honesty and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, were produced, (in opposition to whom, neither <hi>Thou,</hi> nor <hi>Thy fellow Knight of the Post, J—n,</hi> could procure any other than <hi>one single Wench,</hi> and she a Passant-Evidence) who all unanimously attested they were in the Company and Conversation of Mr. <hi>Ireland,</hi> partly in <hi>Staffordshire,</hi> and partly elsewhere, out of <hi>London,</hi> day by day, and every day respectively, from the 4th. of the same <hi>August,</hi> till the 2d. of <hi>Sept.</hi> following.</p>
               <p>Again, Didst thou not swear, thou cam'st over from St. <hi>Omers</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> about the middle of <hi>April</hi> 78. to <hi>London,</hi> where thou lodgedst at <hi>Grove</hi>'s house, (invisibly, for the whole Family attested <hi>they never once saw thee there;</hi>) And having manag'd and dispatch'd in a few days time divers horrid Treasons, returnedst again to St. <hi>Omers</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the same month. In direct contradiction to which frontless Impudence,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> an whole <hi>Cloud of Witnesses,</hi> (and those such whose <hi>Youthful Innocence</hi> cannot rationally be presum'd to have fram'd, learn'd, or even been entrusted with notorious Treacheries and Lies) all gave <hi>Clear</hi> and <hi>Concordant Evidence, That they saw thee, lived with thee, eat with thee, conversed with thee, at St.</hi> Omers, where thou wert entertain'd upon Charity) <hi>every day, without discontinuance, excepting two days, when thou went'st to</hi> Watten) <hi>from</hi> Decemb. 76 <hi>till</hi> June 78. After which time, indeed, thou wert, (as thou know'st) for thy two eminent Qualities of <hi>Dulness of Wit,</hi> and <hi>Dissolution of Manners,</hi> civily <hi>Expelled the Colledge;</hi> in requital for which <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission,</hi> and gratitude for <hi>past Charities</hi> exhibited, thou piously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised'st <hi>to be Reveng'd.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:201976:9"/>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>Well; But did not I bravely shift off the weight of all these Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, by insinuating <hi>the Witnesses were Papists;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> And then, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a <hi>Coach-man,</hi> a <hi>Kitchen-wench,</hi> an acknowledged <hi>Frantick Old Man,</hi> and <hi>Two others,</hi> whom I and my Assistants (especially <hi>Trusty</hi> Sir <hi>William</hi>) pick'd up, to swear, <hi>They thought they saw me here in</hi> March, April, <hi>and</hi> May; the only Months, as to matter of Time, could fall under debate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Those very Witnesses of thine, (besides their being, both in <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> much inferiour to the others) granting them Steady and Coherent in their Depositions, (as they were not) are yet so far from <hi>strengthening thy Forgeries,</hi> or <hi>weakening the contrary Testimonies,</hi> that Thou thy self hast contradicted their Evidence, and <hi>They Thine;</hi> For thou publickly professedst, That thou remainedst all <hi>March</hi> at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and cam'st not from thence into <hi>England</hi> till the 24th. of <hi>April</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Narr.</note>
                  <hi>New stile,</hi> that is the 14th. <hi>Old stile;</hi> That thou landedst at <hi>Dover</hi> on the
<note n="*" place="margin">5 <hi>Jesuits</hi> Tryal.</note> 17th. and coming from thence by Coach, arrivedst not, (by consequence,) at <hi>London,</hi> till at least the 19th. following; That thou wert present at a certain Treasonable Consult (<hi>with</hi> 50 <hi>Jesuits</hi> crowded together) at the <hi>White-horse-Tavern</hi> near <hi>Charing-Cross</hi> on the 24th. of the same <hi>April, Old stile;</hi> And that within three or four
<note n="*" place="margin">Narrat.</note> days precisely after, that is, at farthest, on the 27th. or 28th. of the same month, thou returnedst with the <hi>Fathers</hi> (as thou term'st them) back to St. <hi>Omers:</hi> So that, by thy own calculation, thou could'st not have been above 8 or 9 days in Town; and this within, and towards the latter end of the month of <hi>April.</hi> Now, thy <hi>a-la-mode Witnesses</hi> depose, <hi>They saw, and spoke with thee in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>some in the latter end of</hi> March, <hi>or beginning of</hi> April; <hi>Others in the beginning or middle of</hi> May. Wherefore, unless thou canst prove, (by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coll.</hi> Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>Maberry</hi>'s <hi>Almanack</hi>) that <hi>March, April</hi> and <hi>May</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that year all at one individual time; or at least, that the latter end of <hi>March</hi> or beginning of <hi>April,</hi> and the beginning or middle of <hi>May,</hi> was all within the compass of <hi>Nine days,</hi> and those from the 19th. to the 28th. of <hi>April</hi> inclusive: Thou must confess, either <hi>Thou,</hi> or <hi>Thy Witnesses,</hi> or <hi>Both,</hi> and <hi>All,</hi> are <hi>Perjured Persons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet more. Thou swor'st,
<note n="*" place="margin">5 <hi>Jes.</hi> Tr.</note> Thou cam'st over from St. <hi>Omers</hi> with one <hi>Hilsley,</hi> on the 13th of <hi>June Old stile;</hi> whenas <hi>Hilsley</hi> himself attested, <hi>Thou never cam'st over with him;</hi> and it was proved by at least 15 substantial Witnesses, <hi>Thou remainedst at St.</hi> Omers <hi>several weeks after.</hi> In like manner, thou swor'st, Thon cam'st over into <hi>England</hi> in the Company of
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Sir <hi>Thomas Preston,</hi> Sir <hi>John Warner</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pool,</hi> on the 24th of <hi>April.</hi> whenas it was likewise proved, by Irrefragable Testimonies, <hi>That the birst of these Persons was at</hi> Watten; <hi>The Second at</hi> Leige; <hi>and the Third at St.</hi> Omers, <hi>that very day, and some time immediatly after.</hi> Also thou swor'st,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Mr. <hi>Gaven</hi> was at <hi>London</hi> in <hi>July:</hi> whenas <hi>Gaven</hi> sufficiently proved, (though the Proof was stifled) <hi>He was then in</hi> Staffordshire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>But Thou, as if it were not sufficient to be proved <hi>Perjur'd</hi> by <hi>others Evidence,</hi> must needs prove <hi>Perjury</hi> upon thy self, by <hi>Thy own
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:201976:10"/>positive Testimony.</hi> For, (abating thy various undeniable <hi>Self-Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries</hi> heretofore mentioned) thou expresly
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Tryal.</note> swor'st at <hi>White-hall,</hi> Thou saw'st Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> at a Consult at <hi>Wild-house;</hi> But at his Tryal thou swor'st it again, and said'st it was at Mr. <hi>Fenwick</hi>'s Chamber. So likewise, thou positively swor'st at <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Tryal, Thou never saw'st
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi> after <hi>April</hi> 78; Yet at <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s Tryal, Thou swor'st thou saw'st him twice or thrice in <hi>July</hi> following. That was a Rapper.</p>
               <p>Moreover, thou swor'st in several
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staff</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Depositions, (particularly those taken before the Privy-Councel and House of Lords) thou hadst given an Entire, Exact, and Faithful Account of all thou knew'st of any Person whatsoever concern'd in the <hi>Plot,</hi> amongst whom thou only alledgedst against the Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> That thou hadst seen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond-Seas some Letters sign'd <hi>Stafford,</hi> wherein the Writer had testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in general his Zeal for the <hi>Catholick Design;</hi> But when after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thou and thy Abetters found this Flam would not suffice to draw Innocent Bloud, (not once regarding thy former Oaths) thou wickedly imposedst upon my Lord new-invented Treasons, never mentioned, or thought on before.</p>
               <p>These, and innumerable other <hi>Perjuries</hi> of thine own production, are so convincing, they cannot be deny'd, and so apparent, they cannot be conceal'd; And however a transporting Fervour might, for a while, as it were hood-wink even a Just Court, and well-mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning Jury; (for what Humane Judgment is not, in Moral matters, liable to be abused, and by consequence mis-led, by the Malice and Perjury of Impious Men?) Yet at last the cry of Innocent Bloud hath awakened Heaven and Earth, And the Justice of the Nation; The Injured Government; The Laws of God and Man, Barbarously Prophaned and Violated by Thee, will assuredly overtake thee, and inflict upon thee Punishments <hi>adequate</hi> to thy demerits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>I might still have run on in a Deluge of Bloud, and continued my Impostures, as it were in despight of God and Man, hadst not thou exposed our Evidence to open shame at the fatal Tryal of Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> Mr. <hi>Marshal Rumley,</hi> and <hi>Corker.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Tryal.</note> There it was we lost our Dominion, by thy blind Miscarriages; There it was thy rank Contradictions, Perjuries and Non-sence despoiled us of Credit, and rendred us odious and detestable to all honest thinking Men. Didst thou not, when thou wert called before the King and Councel, and set face to face with Sir <hi>George,</hi> positively affirm, thou knew'st nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>Person</hi> nor his <hi>Hand-writing,</hi> nor hadst any thing to alledge against him, but a Letter writ by a third person, wherein Sir <hi>George</hi> was mention'd? And being a second time cited, and asked by the Councel, whether thou hadst any thing more whereof to accuse Sir <hi>George?</hi> Did thou not again lifting up thy hands and Eyes to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, deliberately and distinctly answer,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>No! God forbid that I should say any thing against Sir</hi> George Wakeman, <hi>for I know nothing more against him?</hi> Notwithstanding which positive and publick Assertion, didst thou not afterwards, at Sir <hi>George</hi>'s Tryal, swear, to the horrour of the whole Court,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> That thou hadst been acquainted with him? That thou knew'st the Character of his hand, and hadst
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:201976:10"/>seen a Treasonable Letter of his writ to Mr. <hi>Ashby?</hi> (which Letter Sir <hi>George</hi> proved, both by Witnesses and Circumstances, he neither <hi>did,</hi> nor <hi>could</hi> write.) That he had a Commission to be Physician-general to the Army? That he had undertaken to poison the <hi>King,</hi> and long bartered with the <hi>Jesuits</hi> about the Price? That they had profer'd him 10000 <hi>l.</hi> which Sir <hi>George</hi> refused, as too little: but at length they struck up a bargain for 15000 <hi>l?</hi> (as if, in a matter whereon the Overthrow of the Government, Laws, Liberties, Lives, and Religion of Three Nations depended, and whereof the main, if not the whole Issue, was committed to Sir <hi>George</hi>'s Artifice, 5000 <hi>l.</hi> could ballance either side.) Thus, without any regard either to thy <hi>former Protestations,</hi> or possibility of the thing, thou swor'st and unswor'st, as if thou intendedst to destroy thy Credit, Body and Soul together.</p>
               <p>The <hi>like,</hi> or <hi>worse,</hi> (if worse could be)
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Contradictions and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdities thou swor'st against Mr. <hi>Marshal</hi> and <hi>Corker;</hi> For when, like <hi>Judas, thou cam'st with a Band of Men and Officers, with Torches, Lanthorns, and Weapons,</hi> to take <hi>Pickering</hi> in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> thou found'st <hi>Marshal</hi> and <hi>Corker</hi> there in the same house; Thou viewedst them; Thou long studiedst and debatedst who they should be; The Officers often demanded if thou hadst any thing to lay to their Charge? To which, after demurring upon the matter, thou at last positively answered'st,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>I know not these Gentlemen; I never saw them before; I have nothing to say against them.</hi> Now, a body would think, after these serious Asseverations, <hi>Marshal</hi> and <hi>Corker</hi> had been (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were) absolute Strangers to thee. Nevertheless, about a Forthnight or Three-weeks after, when, pumping thy Judgement, thou conjecturedst by the place where they were they might be <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictines,</hi> impudently swallowing thy former Asseverations made before the Constables, Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thou deposedst, <hi>Thou hadst seen them; Thou hadst known them; Thou hadst conversed with them; Thou hadst been bellow-Plotter with them in the Lord knows how many damnable impossible Treasons against the</hi> King <hi>and State.</hi> Nay, thou wert so intimate an
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Acquaintance, Bosom-friend, and Councellor to <hi>Corker,</hi> that he shewed thee a Patent from <hi>Rome</hi> for his being Bishop of <hi>London,</hi> and told thee of great Sums of Money he had to distribute, towards carrying on the Conspiracy. Thou farther assertedst,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> That <hi>He</hi> and <hi>Marshal</hi> were both of them guilty of the <hi>Plot;</hi> Both privy to the Design of <hi>Pickering</hi>'s shooting the <hi>King;</hi> Both willing enough the business should be done, but only excepted against the Person to do it; And why? Because (forsooth) whil'st <hi>Pickering</hi> (being a <hi>Lay-Brother</hi>) attended upon the Altar, <hi>an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity might be lost;</hi> (as if whil'st <hi>Pickering</hi> was imploy'd in so Mighty a Work, the Priests could find none to serve them at Mass.)
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Thou swor'st also, That they both agreed to the Payment of 6000 <hi>l.</hi> out of the <hi>Benedictines</hi> Estates, towards driving on the Design. <hi>(a likely story, that the</hi> Benedictines, <hi>who, as His Majesty often acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, had contributed what they were able, to supply His Necessities du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring His Exile, without other hope or prospect of Advantage, then the satisfaction of having discharged their Duty and Loyalty to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed Soveraign: should now give</hi> All, <hi>and probably</hi> More <hi>than they have, to take away His Life.)</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:201976:11"/>
               <p>Furthermore,
<note n="*" place="margin">Narrat</note> thou attestedst, in thy <hi>first Depositions</hi> against <hi>Corker,</hi> That he, on the 17th of <hi>August</hi> 78. actually lodged, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with other <hi>Benedictines,</hi> near the Wardrobe behind the <hi>Savoy;</hi> and did <hi>then</hi> and <hi>there</hi> engage to assist the <hi>Jesuits</hi> with 6000 <hi>l.</hi> in order to the Design. But afterwards, finding by <hi>Corker</hi>'s Examination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Committee, That he had declared, and could prove upon Oath, he had been beyond-Seas from the 5th. of the same <hi>August,</hi> till towards the end of <hi>September</hi> following: Thou quite renversedst at his
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Tryal all thy former Depositions, and swor'st, That he went in <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> to the far-end of <hi>Germany,</hi> and had been with <hi>Monsieur la Chese</hi> and others at <hi>Paris,</hi> (the almost direct contrary way) to give them an account how matters stood in <hi>England;</hi> That whil'st he thus remained beyond-Seas, he writ and sent a Letter to <hi>London</hi> in the latter-end of <hi>August,</hi> wherein,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> as President of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> he gave his consent for the payment of the above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned 6000 <hi>l.</hi> which Letter thou saw'st and read'st, being (as thou foolishly said'st, but could'st not prove,) well acquainted with his Hand. Now, see how thou hast here embrassed thy Evidence with manifold Contradictions and Perjuries. For <hi>First, Corker</hi> was never one day out of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> throughout the whole months of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July</hi> in the year 78. as those who then lived, and daily conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with him in the same place, have attested; And thou wilt find it an hard matter to make People believe he could be both in the <hi>Savoy</hi> and in <hi>Germany</hi> at the self-same time. 2dly. If <hi>Corker</hi> went beyond-Seas (as thou swor'st) in <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July,</hi> and staid there, and writ a Letter from thence the latter-end of <hi>August:</hi> Thou art Perjur'd in thy <hi>first Depositions,</hi> wherein thou swear'st, He was then in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy.</hi> But if he liv'd and lodg'd in the <hi>Savoy</hi> (as thou also swor'st) on the 17th of <hi>August,</hi> thou art Perjured in thy Evidence at his Tryal, wherein thou swoar'st, He was then beyond-Seas; So that which of the two soever is <hi>True</hi> or <hi>False,</hi> thou art <hi>Self-Perjured.</hi> 3dly. Thou swor'st, That <hi>Corker</hi> writ and sent that Letter from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond-Seas, wherein he gave his consent to the raising of 6000 <hi>l.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause being President of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> it was necessary he should give his Suffrage. Now, if <hi>Corker</hi> was (as thou formerly swor'st) personally present at the <hi>Savoy</hi> on the 17th. of <hi>August,</hi> and then and there gave his consent for the raising of that Money: What neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, or even sense, was there, he should a week or ten days after send his Suffrage by a Letter from beyond-Seas? 4thly. Thou putt'st the whole Stress of thy Evidence upon <hi>Corker</hi>'s being President of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> for that, as such, the 6000 <hi>l.</hi> could not be given without him: Now, <hi>Corker,</hi> prov'd by Three (and could have prov'd by Three-score,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> if the Court had required it) That <hi>not He,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Stapilton,</hi> then was, and had been for several years before, President of that Order; So little wast thou conversant in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> and so Rash and Headstrong in swearing to matters whereof thou wert wholly Ignorant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>Could any body swear either more blindly to what they <hi>knew not,</hi> or more falsly to what they <hi>knew,</hi> then thou didst at the same Tryal of <hi>Marshal</hi> and <hi>Corker?</hi> Thou swor'st
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Tryal.</note> that <hi>Corker</hi> was at the <hi>Jesuits
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:201976:11"/>Consult</hi> at the <hi>White-horse-Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Strand</hi> on the 24th. of <hi>April;</hi> whenas <hi>Corker</hi> declar'd, and shew'd by probable Arguments, He was that very time Thirty miles out of Town. Thou swor'st
<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shal</hi> was at another Consult in the <hi>Savoy</hi> on the 14th. or 16th of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust;</hi> whenas he offered, under forfeiture of his Life, to prove by a whole Train of good Witnesses, He was those very particular days in <hi>Warwickshire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, thou could'st not contain thy self within the limits of serious Lies; thou must needs play the <hi>Jack-Pudding</hi> upon the Sacred <hi>Bible,</hi> and swear matters of Farce and Drollery, with Pies and Custards to make Sport for the <hi>Mobile.</hi> Was it not a wonderful refined Conceit and Invention of thine, to swear
<note n="*" place="margin">Narra.</note> Mr. <hi>Coniers</hi> laid a Wager at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> of 100 <hi>l.</hi> with thou knew'st not whom (in which Wager
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>Marshal</hi> went half with <hi>Coniers</hi>) That the Villain the <hi>King</hi> should not live to eat any more <hi>Christmas-Pies?</hi> Surely thou studiedst hard and long at <hi>Salamanca,</hi> before thou could'st attain to these elevated Notions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Thou hadst not best insist much upon my Miscarriages at the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy;</hi> I shall retort it home to thee.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Tryal.</note> Was it not thither thou cam'st with Rags on thy Back, and Stockens out at heels, to beg <hi>Six-pence</hi> for a poor distressed <hi>Catholick?</hi> Wast not thou there, as well as at other Houses of <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> turn'd from the doors, as a Person of an Idle and Debauch'd Life; and this too, as the Devil would have it, just at the very time when thou pretendest to be most entrusted and engaged with the <hi>Popish Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits, Lords</hi> and <hi>Gent.</hi> in the Conspiracy? Was not thus much proved upon thee? Didst thou not thy self publickly own it at my Lord <hi>Stafford</hi>'s <hi>Tryal?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staff.</hi>'s Tryal.</note> And this being so, what Inference, think'st thou, will rational Persons draw from hence?
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staff.</hi>'s Memoi.</note> Could this <hi>Oates</hi> (will they say) be privy to all the grand Commissions? Could he be employ'd in all the deep and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Consults? Could he have at his mercy the Lives and Fortunes of all the chief <hi>Conspirators?</hi> Men stock'd with Banks of Money suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>(if we will believe him)</hi> to raise Armies, and provide for 2 300000 Souldiers? Could this Man nevertheless starve in a manner for Bread? Could he beg for an Alms at the <hi>Papists</hi> doors? Could he want <hi>Two-pence</hi> to clout his Hose? Could he be rejected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned as an idle Vagabond, by the very persons who thus had put their Lives into his hands? <hi>This is such a Paradox as none in their senses will ever believe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, now I remember it,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stafford,</hi> Tryal.</note> tho' thou confessedst (and truly) thou hadst not <hi>Six pence</hi> at thy first discovery of the <hi>Plot;</hi> yet <hi>(O wonder!)</hi> thou swor'st thou wert
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn</hi>'s Tryal.</note> 700 <hi>l.</hi> worse since thy detecting of it: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving expended great Sums on that Account, above what thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivedst in <hi>His Majesty</hi>'s Service. Prithee how would'st thou have People imagine thou could'st come by all this <hi>Treasure</hi> and <hi>Riches,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less thou pick'dst some of Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi>'s 15000 <hi>l.</hi> out of his Pocket at the Councel-Board, or Stol'st from <hi>Corker</hi> his <hi>Contribution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money</hi> at the seizing of <hi>Pickering?</hi> Ungrateful Miscreant! Wast thou not maintained in <hi>Pomp, Riot and Luxury</hi> at <hi>White-hall, upon His Majesty's Charges,</hi> even almost to Reflection on his Bounty and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:201976:12"/>Goodness? And hast thou the face to disown the Benevolence, by <hi>Redoubled Perjuries</hi> known to the whole <hi>Nation?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>Well, But since our Vices and Villainies have excluded us from <hi>White-hall,</hi> thou hast taken such desperate courses to get Money, that at length (if the Gallows do not prevent us) we shall be forced ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to steal, or beg at the <hi>Papists</hi> doors again. Thou hast set to sale thy Oaths as it were by way of <hi>Auction,</hi> or <hi>Inch-of-Candle;</hi> and prostituted thy Evidence to any one would give most for it. How notoriously didst thou act the Hireling, and prophane Sacred Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetes,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coll.</hi> Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>In verbo Sacerdotis; As a Minister of the Gospel,</hi> &amp;c. to serve the <hi>Associated Brethren</hi> with a Cast of thy Office at <hi>Colledge</hi>'s Tryal! And then, into what a Labyrinth of Shame and Confusion hast thou brought both thy self and thy Friend <hi>What-d'ye-call-him</hi> yonder, in swearing, <hi>That</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Elliot</hi>'s Vind.</note>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Elliot <hi>was a Circumcised</hi> Mahumetan-Popish-Priest, <hi>and had escaped from Slavery by Poisoning his</hi> Patrone! A body would think thy formerly experienc'd daily Failures should have taught thee more Wit. Thou seest <hi>Elliot</hi> will not permit himself, without opposition, to be Hang'd, Drawn and Quartered, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance to thee; And he being a Clergy-man of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> People will not so easily yield an implicite Faith to thy Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments against him, as they did against the <hi>Papists,</hi> in matters repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to their five senses. Let me tell thee in short, this Oathing down <hi>Elliot</hi> was a foul business.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>Why, who could foresee, or even dream, That <hi>Elliot</hi>'s Patrone should come personally himself from <hi>Morocco</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> as it were on purpose to detect our <hi>Perjury,</hi> and confound our <hi>Evidence?</hi> Who, I say, could possibly imagine such an unfortunate chance? But thou, independent on all contingency, hast wittingly and willingly preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated into Ruine the small remainder of our Credit beyond all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trievement. When thou wert heated and puffed up with Blood, Wine, Sedition and Arrogance, thou must needs, like a Fool, burn thy Fingers, in Roguing, Rascalling and Popifying the <hi>Observator;</hi> a Person of that Eminent Learning, Publick Merit, and known Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to the Established Government, Laws and Church of <hi>England,</hi> that he is as far above <hi>Thy Calumny,</hi> as thou art beneath <hi>His Worth</hi> and <hi>Honesty.</hi> Surely the Devil ow'd thee an ill turn, when he egg'd thee on to this Rashness; For what can a Villain, like thee, expect less then fatal, from such an <hi>Head,</hi> such an <hi>Heart,</hi> such an <hi>Hand,</hi> as that of <hi>L'Estrange?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>There is a certain Antipathy between Virtue and Vice; And I (as thou know'st) not having one Dram either of Wit, Learning, Worth or Honesty, can never speak well of any Person endued with those Qualities. But Thou, and thy unnatural Companions, like Ravening Wolves have devoured one another, and so rent and torn each others Testimony, that nothing but a Rope can fix you together again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dugdale</hi>'s <hi>Evidence</hi> hath got a Clap, and now <hi>his Credit</hi> as well as <hi>his Person</hi> is rotten. Thou thy self (like a Cocxomb) gav'st <hi>Him,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:201976:12"/>Turbervil, Smith</hi> and <hi>Hayns</hi> their Deaths-wounds at <hi>Colledge's</hi> Tryal;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coll.</hi> Tryal.</note> And they as well returned thy kindness; For as thou swor'st <hi>Them,</hi> so they swore <hi>Thee</hi> in open Court, Guilty of <hi>Perjury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into the like Predicament hast thou also brought thy Two Northern Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, <hi>Balron</hi> and <hi>Maberry;</hi> who, tho' formerly well-<hi>Gascoign'd</hi> Witnesses, yet running counter, together with Thee, in that untoward Tryal of <hi>Colledge,</hi> were so Hamstring'd in their Evidence, the poor Curs can now cramble no farther.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Irish Witnesses,</hi> (those of them, I mean, that remain yet unhang'd)
<note place="margin">Several Narrat.</note> Thou hast spoil'd <hi>Their Evidence,</hi> and They <hi>Thine,</hi> in swearing off and on, in direct Opposition to each other, about my Lord of <hi>Ormond.</hi> So that, in fine, I say, you can never combine well together, unless upon the Gallows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
               <p>No wonder to find Incoherence of Parts in a Story divested of Truth. Alas! Thou know'st, I, and the rest of my Brethren, both <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Irish,</hi> of the <hi>Swearing Tribe,</hi> were only a Generation of Vipers, tainted with all manner of Crimes; A Company of Infamous Persons, of lost Consciences, and desperate Fortunes; Raked out of Goals, and varnished over with the specious Title of the <hi>Kings</hi>'s <hi>Evidence;</hi> encouraged with hopes of Pardon for the foulest Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours; Allured by the Prospect of Present Gain; Retrieved from pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Want and Misery; Transported with Popular Applause; Instigated and abetted by the undermining Policies, and restless endeavours of the Enemies of the Government; To amuse the Nation; to affright honest Men; to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Ignorant; to oppress the Innocent; to abuse the Laws; to injure the Magistrates; to disturb the Church and State; to raise Intestine Broils, and push on a <hi>New Rebellion</hi> by the <hi>Old Methods</hi> of Lies, and Clamours of imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Dangers and inevitable Ruine of our Liberties, Lives and Religion, from <hi>Popish Invasions, Arbitrary Powers, Dreadful Chymoera's,</hi> and <hi>Horrid Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasms</hi> of no body knows what. And though we had neither Credibility of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, nor Probity of Manners, <hi>(Two necessary Ingredients to a good Evidence)</hi> whereby to strengthen our Monstrous Testimonies: Yet, whilst the Case was <hi>Popery;</hi> whilst we gave Attestation against <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits;</hi> whilst we kissed the <hi>Sacred Bible,</hi> and invoked <hi>God</hi> to <hi>help us,</hi> according to the Truth of our Depositions, whilst Zeal possessed some, Fear or Malice others, and deference to Authority restrained the rest: We might at last have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed the Treacherous Designs of our Ring-leaders; And by heightning of Jealousies, raising of Animosities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have intoxicated Mens minds to that degree, as <hi>to make</hi> English <hi>Protestants destroy one another, to avoid</hi> Popish Massacres. We might, I say, as our Affairs once stood, have effected this, and thereby have notably served both the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Dissenters,</hi> hadst thou not, by thy acknowledged Impious Practices, defiled and prophaned the only thing that sanctifies an Oath, <hi>(viz.) Religion,</hi> and rendred <hi>Protestanism,</hi> through thy owning of it, more Deformed, Polluted and Odious then ever <hi>Popery</hi> could hitherto be represented by any Invectives of its greatest Adversaries. Say, (amphibious Animal:) Say, (Caitiff,) Didst thou not swear,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Staffords</hi> Tryal.</note>
                  <hi>That though thou seemingly went'st over to the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, the better to make Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries) yet thou still interiourly remainedst a Real, Constant, and Substantial Protestant?</hi> Nevertheless, with the same Breath, (O shame and horrour of Mankind!) thou solemnly swor'st <hi>Thou livedst amongst the</hi> Papists, <hi>as one of their Church and Communion; Thou exteriourly professedst their Faith; Thou publickly renouncedst and abjuredst the</hi> Protestant Religion; <hi>Thou exercisedst the</hi> Popish <hi>manner of Worship, Thou receivedst and adoredst the Consecrated Host,</hi> (which, in the judgment both of <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> was in thee, <hi>so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,</hi> direct and gross Idolatry; <hi>Thou took'st</hi> (as thou saist) <hi>dreadful Oaths, even upon the Sacrament, to pursue with all thy Might most Hellish and Bloody Designs: And all this without any Remorse or Intermission for divers years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Are these the Actions of a good and sincere <hi>Protestant?</hi> Is this the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Integrity of the <hi>King's Chief Evidence?</hi> Is this the Piety of a Minister of the Gospel? Are these the Symptoms of a <hi>Reformed Religion?</hi> Or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:201976:13"/>rather, Is there any, either <hi>Protestant, Papist, Turk</hi> or <hi>Devil,</hi> besides thy self, capable of such detestable Sacriledge and Villany?</p>
               <p>This is not all; Thou could'st not be contented with the sole Trade of Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Hypocrisie and Sacriledge in the highest Degree: but thou must needs proclaim thy self an Infidel too. Thou hadst not the Wit to keep to thy self the Atheistical Tenet believed in private between <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Me, (viz) <hi>That the Crucifixion of Christ is nothing available to Salvation;</hi>
                  </hi> But thou must needs in express terms, in the presence of a numerous Auditory, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly preach this execrable Doctrine, in a Sermon before the Company of <hi>Weavers.</hi> What Christian-ears, think'st thou, will endure such Blasphemy? Or what credit will hereafter be given to a Monster inur'd to such Perfidie and Atheism?</p>
               <p>But stay; Let me see; now when I think on it: What, if after all, there should be such a Thing as a <hi>God;</hi> A Revenger; Another World; An immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal state of Bliss or Misery? Certainly there will come a time, (and we know not how soon) when we must depart from hence, never, never more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again. (Woful Wretches!) Whither shall we go? What course shall we take? I fear we shall meet with No <hi>Ignoramus-Juries;</hi> No <hi>Whig-Sheriffs;</hi> No <hi>Kings of Poland,</hi> (though One be lately gone by the way of <hi>Holland</hi> to the Devil already;) No <hi>Foul-mouth'd Cares;</hi> No <hi>Colledges,</hi> No <hi>Janeways, Ealdwins,</hi> or <hi>Curtisses;</hi> No <hi>Hunts,</hi> or <hi>Hickeringils;</hi> No <hi>Suborn'd Witnesses;</hi> No <hi>blind Zeals,</hi> No <hi>Time-serving Interests;</hi> No <hi>State-shams,</hi> No <hi>Praepossessions;</hi> No <hi>Jealousies;</hi> No <hi>Mistakes,</hi> No <hi>Robert Hogs;</hi> to help us out at a dead lift. Every thing that before supported our Credit, will now advance our Torments, (Alas!) Who shall secure us from the Devils, or (the worst of Enemies) our cursed Selves? How shall we shift off our enormous Villainies? Where shall we find Succour, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, Compassion, or Mercy? O Eternity! O worm of Conscience! O Load of Blood! Of Lusts! Of Injustice! Of Sacriledge! Of Sins Immense and Numberless! O Death and Judgement! O Fire and Damnation! O Divine Vengeance! Who shall endure it?</p>
               <p>For <hi>Beelzebub</hi> our grand Master's sake do not fright and torture <hi>Thy self</hi> and <hi>Me</hi> with these hideous Objects: They too often, in despight of my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to the contrary, seize upon my trembling Soul. Come, I see <hi>Thou</hi> and <hi>I</hi> must never be alone together. Call in the Varlets that usually attend us: Let us shake off these Dismal Corroding Thoughts: Let us strive to be careless and senseless of the next Life. We are already Sons of Perdition, and cannot be much worse then we are. If there be no <hi>God,</hi> or Supreme Deity, Wise, Powerful and Just, we are well enough. But if there be, (as in spight of my heart I doubt there is) we cannot help it; Damnation is our Lot, and there's an end. Nay, though there should be such a thing as a Christian Faith and Law: what are we the better for it? Thou know'st we neither believe, nor were ever baptized, and by consequence can challenge no right to the Passion of <hi>Christ;</hi> And from what other Fountain can spring any hope? We may indeed profess <hi>Presbyterianism,</hi> as the Religion most proper and connatural to our present mischievous Purposes. But, in reality, there is no access for us to <hi>God,</hi> Let us then make the best use of our short time. Over Shoes, over Boots. Let us defie Heaven, and drown our selves in Vice and Sensuality, till at length, Divine Justice overtake us; Vengeance seizes us; The Devil claim his due; And we finally sink down headlong into Hell: there to Burn, Howl, Rage, Curse and Blaspheme for ever.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="anagram">
            <p>
               <hi>An</hi> Anagram, <hi>Composed by a Person of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SALAMANKYES DEVIL DOCTOR TITUS OATES, DISCORD ON A STATE LYE WIL MAKE AL SOTTS.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>